なんば
むった
《あと30分で最終試験の➡
In thirty minutes, they'll start announcing the final exam results.
結果発表がはじまる…➡
ジャクサ
私達 受験生にＪＡＸＡから
順次 電話がかかってくるのだ…》
Each candidate will receive a phone call from JAXA.
今日は お昼ヤキソバだから｡➡
We're having yakisoba for lunch today.
あのさ～ 今日は
試験の合格発表だよ｡
Uh...
You realize they're announcing the results today?
もうちょっと こう…
えんぎ
縁起のいいヤツあるでしょう➡
Shouldn't we have something more lucky?
カツ丼的なさ…｡
(母)合格したら…➡
Like katsudon maybe?
If you pass, I'll buy you a cake.
ケーキ買ってあげるわよ！
That's because you feel like eating cake...
《それ か～ちゃんが
食いて～だけじゃね～かよ》
焼いてないでしょう➡
Yakisoba is a wonderful thing.
カップヤキソバ 大～好き～
Yudesoba is boiled, not stir-fried.
But I love cup yakisoba!
(母)フフ…アッハハハ｡
Seven Days
Space Brothers
Before my uneasiness
was the end
of my happiness
I came to you
and we were one
Hello Hello
Let's fly
Here in this world we dream
and keep on dancing
Here among light and shadow
we keep changing
so that the wind doesn't let up
Even though the future is vague and unreliable
we are
not alone
#35 From the Little Corner of a Big Facility
(鶴見)原田君｡
(原田)あ…はい｡
Harada.
Y-Yes?
ほしか
星加のヤツ 見てないか？
もうすぐ発表なんだがな｡
Have you seen Hoshika?
It's almost time to announce the results.
星加さん 今 会議が長引いてて
まだ しばらくかかると思います｡
Hoshika's stuck in a meeting, so he won't be available for a while.
フッ そうか｡あいつ
今頃 早く終わらせたくて➡
All right...
I'm sure he's dying to get out of there.
ウズウズしてんだろうな｡
では 今日の記者会見
皆さん よろしく お願いします｡➡
That concludes our guidance for today's press conference.
セス
ＣＥＳ-５１に注目が
集まっていることもあって➡
Due to the attention CES-51 has attracted,
今回は普段より多くの記者が
取材にくることが予想されます｡➡
we do expect more journalists than usual.
準備は予定通りに
進んでおりますが…｡
Preparations are proceeding on schedule.
フゥ～…｡
よし！
Okay.
ふうか
い～えふじ～➡
れろれろれろれろぴ～
アッハハハ…｡
い～えふじ～
☎(鶴見)
どうも ＪＡＸＡの鶴見です｡
Hello?
Hello, this is Tsurumi, from JAXA.
まかべ
はい 真壁です｡
Yes, this is Makabe.
☎(鶴見)
以前 お伝えした通り 今日は
宇宙飛行士選抜の結果を➡
As previously mentioned, I am calling today to inform you of the final exam results.
お知らせするために
連絡させて頂きました｡
(ケンジ)はい｡
Yes.
《この電話…この一本の電話から
俺の毎日は…》
This call...
This single phone call
might change everything...
...about my life.
(ケンジ)《変わるかもしれない》
(ケンジ)＜俺の一日は
朝の６時半に始まる＞
My day always began at 6:30 AM.
おはよう｡
(ユキ)おはよう｡
Morning...
Good morning.
＜顔を洗い ヒゲを剃って…＞
I would wash my face, shave,
＜いつもの髪型にセット＞
and do my hair as always.
(ユキ)ケンちゃん
パンくらい食べたら？
Ken, have some toast before you leave.
あっ ごめん｡時間ないや｡
Sorry, I don't have time.
＜朝食は日によって
食べたり食べられなかったり＞
Sometimes, I'd leave without eating breakfast.
Here are your work clothes.
(ユキ)これ 作業着｡
サンキュ｡
Thanks.
おはよ 風佳｡
ウッフフ｡
Daddy!
Good morning, Fuuka.
(風佳)パ～パ！
Bye-bye!
Be careful!
いってらっしゃい｡
しゃ～い！エヘッ｡➡
Sye!
しゃ～い！フフッ…｡
＜通勤ラッシュは俺には無縁だ｡➡
I never had to worry about rush hour.
職場は郊外｡➡
I work in the suburbs.
So the train was always empty.
下りの電車は
いつだって空いている＞
A shuttle would take me from the station to my workplace.
もより
＜職場に最寄の駅からは
会社のシャトルバスに乗る＞
じゅうたい
(ケンジ)＜渋滞のない１本道｡
職場の周りには➡
There's never much traffic to stress over.
There aren't any supermarkets, restaurants, or landmarks where I work.
スーパーもレストランも
なが
眺める景色もない＞
Photochemistry Lab
No Smoking
Makabe
どうりょう
(同僚)なんだよ 真壁｡
自分の作業着姿➡
What are you doing, Makabe?
Admiring the way you look in the suit?
イケてるわ～って思ってんの？
入社８年目にして｡ハハッ｡
You've been here for eight years.
アッハハ…まさか｡
That isn't it.
《むしろ その逆》
Actually, I feel the opposite way.
(同僚)あ～あ…天気
悪り～なぁ～ もう｡
Man...
The weather sucks.
Yeah, it kills your motivation.
ああ｡テンション下がるな｡
＜俺の仕事場は…
だだっ広い施設の ほんの一角＞
I work in
the little corner
of a big facility.
(ケンジ)＜仕事は好きで
やっていることだ｡➡
I enjoy my job.
ほこ
当然 楽しくて誇りも持っている｡➡
I'm proud of the work I do.
定時には帰宅できるし
かんきょう
恵まれた環境とも言える｡➡
I'm able to go home on time, so I consider myself fortunate.
だけど…俺は…＞
But I...
今日 弁当？
(ケンジ)いや…今日は｡
Did you bring a lunch today?
No, not today.
Then let's go to the cafeteria.
じゃあ 食堂 行こうぜ｡
食堂しかないけどな
Not like we have a choice!
(ケンジ)＜他の研究員達は
皆 あきらめてるか➡
The other researchers must have given up,
全く 気にしていない様子だ｡➡
because they don't seem to mind.
Katsudon
Curry
Combo A
社員食堂のメニューの
ワンパターンさや➡
Not the cafeteria's lack of variety,
今日の曇り空に同化しそうな
グレーの➡
nor the gray uniforms that blend right in
この…地味な制服のこととか➡
with the dreary sky.
Something doesn't feel quite right.
やっぱり なんか
ちょっと違うんだよな…＞
What will you have?
何定食？
あっ Ａです｡
Combo A.
(ケンジ)＜やっぱり なんか
ちょっと違うんだよ＞
Something definitely doesn't feel quite right.
＜子供の頃に想像してた➡
This isn't what I wanted to do when I grew up.
“大人の自分"は もっと…こう＞
(同僚)なんだ みんなＡ定食か？
I wanted something more.
(同僚)でも 俺のは大盛りだぜ｡
(同僚)フッ｡お前 いつも
そうじゃねぇかよ｡
(ケンジ)＜ぶっ飛んでた‼＞
To soar...
《そうだ ぶっ飛んでたよな
意味もなく…》
Yeah, I just wanted to soar.
《このまま ここを一生の仕事場と
決めてしまって いいのか？》
Do I want to spend the rest of my life working here?
(同僚)ほい ソース｡
Here's the sauce.
《何の ひっかかりもなく…》
Can I truly say
(同僚)はい｡
(ケンジ)《堂々と言えるか…？》
that this is what I want?
(同僚)わりぃ 真壁｡
Sorry, Makabe.
Is this really my dream job?
《これが…
俺の一生の仕事ですって…》
現在
☎(鶴見)…というわけで➡
As you know,
しんさ
今回の最終審査までは
ご存知の通り８人が残りました｡
eight candidates remained at the beginning of the final exam.
はい｡
Yes.
☎(鶴見)
まず ヒューストンでの審査で➡
We asked current astronauts in Houston to help evaluate the candidates.
現役の宇宙飛行士達に
評価をしてもらいました｡➡
それを日本に持ち帰り
ＪＡＸＡの審査員が➡
Their impressions were sent back to Japan, and the JAXA judges scored those opinions.
評価を数値化しました｡
はい｡
Right.
☎(鶴見)え～ それを３次試験の
へいさ
閉鎖ボックスの時に➡
And then those numbers were added to your scores from the third stage in the sealed boxes...
我々がつけた点数と合わせ
総合点として…｡
《前置きが やけに長いな｡
早く 結果を言ってくれよ》
I don't need this long introduction...
Just tell me if I passed!
《ダメだから
遠まわしに話すのか…》
Is he taking so long because I wasn't chosen?
《俺は落ちたのか それとも…》
Did I get dropped?
Or...
You dropped something!
(ユキ)落ちましたよ｡
Huh?
(ケンジ)＜妻のユキとは
大学時代に出会った＞
I met my wife, Yuki, in college.
(ユキ)これ｡
Look.
Oh...
はい｡
(ケンジ)ありがとう｡
Here.
Thank you.
(友達)なあ 夏どうする 今年？
Hey, what are you doing this summer?
I plan to go up to the mountains.
俺…山 行こうと
思ってるんだ｡
あっ いいよね｡軽井沢とか｡
Sounds good. Are you thinking of Karuizawa?
どこ？
エベレスト｡
Where?
Everest.
What? Seriously?
は～…マジで!?
That's one tall mountain.
山っつっても
登りすぎでしょう｡
こういうとこ 良くない？
What do you think of this place?
Wow, it's beautiful!
(友達)どれ？
Lemme see.
じゃあ 先行くね｡
I'm off, then.
じゃあね｡
Bye.
Ah...
どうも｡
こんにちは｡
Hi.
Hello.
How did you know that I'm in the same year?
(ユキ)どうして 同学年って
わかったんですか？
Huh?
(ケンジ)えっ!?いや その…
ピピｯとね ひらめくんだ｡
Oh...
I just kind of knew.
It just hit me.
(ケンジ)やっぱり変だよね｡
I guess that sounds strange.
No, I think it's interesting.
ううん 面白いですよ すごく｡
Not really, uh...
(ケンジ)いやぁ｡えっと…｡
It's Arai.
(ユキ)新井です｡新井ユキ｡
Arai Yuki.
I'm Makabe...
真壁です｡真壁ケンジ｡
Makabe Kenji.
＜こうして俺達は少しずつ➡
Little by little,
同じ時間を
過ごすようになっていった＞
we began spending more time together.
(ユキ)へぇ グランドキャニオン
行ったんだ｡
Wow, you've been to the Grand Canyon?
Yeah.
And now you're going to Everest?
それで今度はエベレスト？
Yep.
そう｡
観光用のトレッキングコースで➡
There's a tourist trail that takes you over 5,000 meters high.
5000メートル以上のところまで
登れるんだ｡
実際に行けば 本とかネットには
載っていないことが山ほどある｡
You can see so much in person that can't be found in books or online.
That's what I want to learn.
それを知りたいんだ｡
Sounds wonderful.
(ユキ)いいね…｡
Yuki, if you're interested...
ユキちゃん 興味があったら…➡
...you should come along.
行った方がいいよ｡
行かないよりは｡
Better to go than not.
(ユキ)ケンちゃん
卒業旅行どうする？
Ken, where do you want to go for our graduation trip?
Hmm?
行きたいとこっていったら…➡
The only place left
would be space.
あとは宇宙かな｡
知ってる｡
I know.
But let's go somewhere close.
でもま 近場でいいよ｡
We can use the chance to do some house hunting.
旅行より 家探しとかしよう｡
Let's find somewhere between our jobs.
俺の会社とユキの会社の
真ん中くらいでさ｡
(ケンジ)＜就職後 しばらくして
俺とユキは結婚した＞
Yuki and I got married shortly after I began working.
ただいま～｡
I'm home.
Daddy!
パパ！パッパー‼
ハハッ 風佳｡ただいま｡
Fuuka, I'm home.
お帰りなさい｡
ただいま｡
Welcome home.
I'm home.
＜宇宙飛行士選抜の情報は
ユキが見つけてくれた＞
Yuki was the one who found the information on the astronaut selection exam.
ねぇ ケンちゃん
ここ見てよ ホラ！
Say, Ken...
Look at this... Here!
Recruiting Astronauts Help Pave Our Future
ホントだ！
ホントダッ！
You're right!
See?
ケンちゃん ずっと
宇宙行きたいって言ってたじゃん｡
You've always wanted to go to space.
受けてみれば？
Why don't you apply?
Recruiting Astronauts Help Pave Our Future
Are you sure, Yuki?
(ケンジ)いいのかよ？ユキ｡
Astronauts risk their lives.
宇宙飛行士ってのは命がけだし➡
And the pay isn't that great, so I wouldn't be making as much.
だけど その割に給料は
それほど良くもなくて➡
今より減るかもしれない｡➡
You're anticipating having to travel overseas a lot.
それに やたらと海外を飛び回って
訓練の日々で➡
And with all the training, I wouldn't have as much time to spend with you two.
家族と過ごせる時間も
今より相当減るんだよ｡➡
それでも いいのかよ｡
Would it really be okay?
ここで私が何て言っても
絶対受けるんでしょ ケンちゃん｡
You're applying no matter what I say, since you already cut out the ad.
You should do it.
もう記事
切り取ってるじゃん それ｡
Recruiting
Astronauts
Help Pave Our Future
受けた方がいいね
受けないよりは｡
Better to apply than not to.
現在
Daddy? Daddy?
し～っ ダメよ‼
Shh, don't talk!
When I made the decision to apply,
＜宇宙飛行士選抜試験を受けると
決めたあの日から➡
俺の毎日は 少し変わったんだ｡➡
my life began to change.
１日の始まりは少し早くなった｡➡
My day began slightly earlier.
顔を洗い ヒゲを剃って…＞
I would wash my face, shave...
＜いつもの髪型にセット＞
And do my hair as always.
っしゃ！
Okay!
(ケンジ)＜少しの時間だけど
勉強を進める＞
Then I would spend my little free time studying.
ケンちゃん ごはん｡
Ken, time for breakfast.
これ 作業着｡
サンキュ｡
Here are your work clothes.
Thanks.
おはよう 風佳｡
Daddy!
Good morning, Fuuka.
I'm leaving.
いってきます｡
しゃ～い！
Sye!
Be careful.
いってらっしゃ～い｡
しゃ～い！
Sye!
I'm off.
いってきま～す｡
しゃ～い！しゃ～い！
Sye!
(ケンジ)＜それでも まだ余裕｡➡
I still have plenty of time.
家から会社までは
だいたい１時間｡➡
The commute to work is about an hour.
この通勤時間が意外と使える＞
I was able to make use of this time.
＜職場の周りには
スーパーもレストランも➡
There weren't any supermarkets, restaurants, or landmarks where I work.
眺める景色もない｡➡
でも 俺の胸には
眺める景色ができた｡➡
But now, there's a landmark in my mind!
もし俺が
宇宙飛行士になれたら…＞
If I could become an astronaut...
《なんて ぶっ飛んだ未来だ！》
A future where I can soar!
(ケンジ)＜俺は あの場所を
飛び出したい｡➡
I want
to escape...
from the little corner of a big facility.
だだっ広い施設の
ほんの一角から➡
俺のモヤモヤを…➡
I want to go somewhere
ぶっ飛ばせるほどの場所へ！＞
I can feel free!
現在
☎(鶴見)というわけで
真壁さんの結果ですが…｡
And now for the results, Makabe.
はい…➡
Yes.
はい…｡
はい…はい…了解しました｡➡
Yes.
I understand.
はい…それでは失礼します｡
Yes.
Goodbye.
Thank you.
Well?
(ユキ)どうだった？
ごめん｡
Sorry.
(ケンジ)ゴホッ ゴホッ…➡
ほんとに謝るよ｡
I really am
sorry about this...
これから しばらくは➡
It's going to get busy,
忙しくて ２人に迷惑かけそうだ｡
so I won't have as much time for you.
合格だ！
(２人)やった～‼
I passed!
Congrats, Ken!
Thanks.
(ケンジ)ありがとう｡アハハハ…｡
第一号は真壁君…と｡
The first call was to Makabe.
Then, moving on to the next one.
さあ 切り替えて
次の電話だ｡え～っと…｡
Let's see...
＜今までの自分の世界が
これからもっと広がっていく｡➡
My world is about to expand...
だだっ広い施設の
ほんの一角から…➡
From the little corner of a big facility
宇宙へと！➡
to the entire universe.
グレーの作業着を脱ぎ
次に着るのは…➡
I'll be graduating from those gray work clothes,
and donning that blue jumpsuit
宇宙飛行士だけが
着ることを許された➡
ブルーのジャンプスーツ｡➡
that only astronauts can wear...
As blue as
今日の空に溶け込みそうな➡
this brilliant sky!
真っ青なヤツだ＞
My right hand spent its days afraid of losing something
but wished to be held by my left hand
I lead you by the hand
Is my hand only there to hold my own hand now?
I can't lose it
Amidst my nagging disappointment that I can do nothing
I felt I wanted to do something
I let go again
I'm not alone in this world
If my hands can only hold two things
then I hope one of them is you
Not alone, not alone
I want our hearts to be connected
I want to be connected
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#36 Dancing Astronaut
＜宇宙飛行士最終試験の
合格発表＞
The final exam results are being announced.
How did Kenji do?
＜どうだったんだろう ケンジ…
それから せりかさんは…＞
And what about Serika?
You're going to become an astronaut, Serika?
りんぺい
＜せりかは
宇宙飛行士になるんだな 将来＞
Yep, a dancing astronaut!
＜そう！踊る宇宙飛行士＞
(まちこ)＜あなた…＞
＜お父さん？＞
Dear?
Dad?
＜せりか
日記を書いてくれないか｡➡
Serika, could you start a journal?
父さん ちょっと
入院が長引きそうなんだ＞
It looks like I'll be in the hospital for a while.
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Dancing Astronaut"
＜ねぇ お父さん
私が お父さんの病気 治す！＞
Hey, Dad...
I'm going to cure you!
ひびと
(南波日々人)パンパカパーン！
This Week's Space Photo
A mysterious capsule lands from outer space?
This week's space photo!
今週の宇宙写真です！
なんじゃこりゃ？
What's that?